<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Topological 4-Geon Theory Unchained</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/</link><description>Geon Theory Development</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright © 2022, Bijou Murray Smith; All rights reserved.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Standard Model, part-1</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/200_standard_model/</link><pubDate>Mon, 26 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/200_standard_model/</guid><description>It has been a cherished goal of mine for years to write this chapter, and subsequent. But I have not developed the theory to my own satisfaction. I do have a bunch of references that I would like to synthesize.
The latest was the classification paper I found by Pezzaglia. I have found a lot of old (pre-2000) papers on the Standard Model families, stuff by the enigmatic Berndt Schmeikal, and Geoffrey Dixon, Trayling and Bayliss, and others.</description></item><item><title>Dirac Solver</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/101_diracpp/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/101_diracpp/</guid><description>The generally advised method for exploiting geometric algebra spinors to numerically solve the Dirac equation is to advance the wave-function in frequency space.
The spinor is after all a field with multivector values defined across all space. The solution can then be advanced via a Fourier Transform with a time update.
The dirac++ code Doran, Gull, Lasenby and Somaroo developed a geometric algebra solver in the 1990&amp;rsquo;s but their code is not available.</description></item><item><title>Quantum Logic, Part-1</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/099_quantum_logic/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/099_quantum_logic/</guid><description>This is only an article stub.
TODO: unfinished. Work in progress. In this chapter I plan to explain how T4G theory yields quantum logic.
Lattices of Propositions How Measurements are like propositions Quantum Logic is a Non-distributive lattice TODO I do not have a Part-2 yet, not sure if it will be needed, except to respond to reader questions.
Next chapter (Dirac Solvers) Previous chapter (Electron Tunnelling) Back to Theory TOC</description></item><item><title>Electron Tunnelling</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/012_electron_tunnelling/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/012_electron_tunnelling/</guid><description>Electron tunnelling is an awesome phenomenon, and there&amp;rsquo;s more to it than we can probably do justice, but I will try to get to the GA simulations and then some of the popular science stuff surrounding associated time-travel claims.
The first half is straight-forward. We will just use the same software for solving the Dirac equation and show what happens to the electron streamlines. As in the previous chapter, there&amp;rsquo;s no accounting for this in orthodox QM.</description></item><item><title>Spin Measurement, Part-2 - Simulation</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/011_spin_measurement_part2/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/011_spin_measurement_part2/</guid><description>Building on Spin Measurements Part-1 and everything else in-between, we now take a look at numerical experiments that help justify T4G theory as a realistic theory which derives most of quantum mechanics from gravity + CTCs.
However, in this chapter I&amp;rsquo;m not going to do anything original. What we&amp;rsquo;ll do is take a look at Doran &amp;amp; Gull&amp;rsquo;s work on simulating Dirac wave packets, which help show that any statistical interpretation, along the lines of Ballentine&amp;#39;s, will have a Stern-Gerlach filter effect that looks like intrinsic discrete spin but which can be taken instead as &amp;ldquo;revealing&amp;rdquo;$^\ast$ the spin current of an electron, or any charged particle, is a statistical polarization effect.</description></item><item><title>Dirac-Hestenes-Greider Spinors</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/010_hestenes_spinors/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/010_hestenes_spinors/</guid><description>This is going to be a loooong chapter, buckle up, grab a drink, permit a few days of eyeball time (unless you are some sort of savant).
The promise is that after some exciting diversions in NRQM, that were foundational for T4G theory, we now want to see if Dirac spinors (four component complex column vectors) exist in timespace algebra with the same algebra as the Dirac matrices. The Dirac matrices ($\hat{\gamma}_\mu$) being the basis for the linear operators which act on the Dirac spinors ($|\phi\rangle$).</description></item><item><title>Interference from Entanglement</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/009_interference_from_entanglement/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/009_interference_from_entanglement/</guid><description>Worth reading the previous chapter on Pauli Exclusion before this one.
Here we use the same idea that isotropically spin-correlated 4-geons are connected by an ER=EPR wormhole bridge. While the previous chapter derived from this hypothesis the Pauli Exclusion Principle, in this chapter we show that the same physics (entanglement via wormholes) leads to double-slit interference.
These insights were made long ago by Paul O&amp;#39;Hara, and we will follow his work, basically just shamelessly reproducing it for popular consumption.</description></item><item><title>Spin-Statistics in Geometric Algebra</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/008_pauli_in_ga/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/008_pauli_in_ga/</guid><description>To denote a system with two indistinguishable particles we need a pair of spacetime frame vectors, since each particle carries it&amp;rsquo;s own clock.
((Why is that? Well, remember in QM/QFT all fundamental particles are &amp;ldquo;oscillators&amp;rdquo; and in T4G theory they all are assumed to have an internal CTC structure which permits geometrodynamic oscillations, which are very much like string vibrations in M-Theory. But this is not really the reason why we need a copy of a spacetime fame for each particle.</description></item><item><title>Pauli Exclusion from Entanglement</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/007_pauli_ex_entanglement/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/007_pauli_ex_entanglement/</guid><description>The necessary background for this chapter is a course on advanced quantum mechanics. But you do not need the whole course. Just the foundations and up to treatments of Hilbert spaces and spin states is sufficient, which is mostly logic and linear algebra, no dynamics needed. However, I thought it much more sensible and rational to use the geometric STA approach to spin, and so even if you have advanced QM background (Sakurai or Ballentine) I would recommend checking out my previous chapter on Pauli algebra and on spin measurement, and then you&amp;rsquo;ll be able to follow the &amp;mdash; in many ways nicer &amp;mdash; account of Pauli exclusion or spin&amp;ndash;statistics in the next chapter, when we repeat this current chapter using geometric algebra.</description></item><item><title>Spin Measurement, part-1 - Projection</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/006_spin_measurement_part1/</link><pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/006_spin_measurement_part1/</guid><description>Building on the previous chapter about spinors in the Paul algebra, we now take a look at measurement of 4-geon spin, and suggest why there is not necessarily a &amp;ldquo;proof positive&amp;rdquo; that spin is discrete in quantum theory. The &amp;ldquo;quantum number&amp;rdquo; for &amp;ldquo;spin&amp;rdquo; is viewed as arising from topology, or the group (symmetry) structure, not from any fundamental discrete ontology.
This is crucial, since it will eventually brings us in a virtuous &amp;ldquo;full circle&amp;rdquo; back to the promise of T4G theory &amp;mdash; which was that most of the weirdness of quantum mechanics dissolves when we try better to see quantum mechanics as a theory of gravity but endowed with particle-like topological 4-geon structure down at the Planck scale.</description></item><item><title>Spacetime and Pauli Algebra</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/005_spacetime_algebra/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/005_spacetime_algebra/</guid><description>A good back-up reference on spacetime algebra (STA) is the classic book by David Hestenes Spacetime Algebra. There is a free article length preprint Spacetime physics with geometric algebra, here. Please do note that I prefer the general relativist&amp;rsquo;s metric convention $(-\!+\!++)$ whereas Hestenes, Doran and Lasenby use the particle physics convention $(+\! -\! -\,-)$. This makes a difference in some of the fussy details for the Lie Algebra commutation relations, which although a headache, can be a good exercise for you to get straight at least in your own private notes.</description></item><item><title>Geometric Algebra</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/004_geometric_algebra/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/004_geometric_algebra/</guid><description>If you are not satisfied with this introduction please consider getting the textbook Geometric Algebra for Physicists, or browse the collection of free articles on the Cambridge GA group website or on David Hestenes&amp;#39; website. A New Langauge or the Language for Physics? Geometric Algebra is described by Hestenes, Doran and Lasenby as the unified language for physics. But in my view it is tantamount to the language, and that&amp;rsquo;s because I think all physics is geometry.</description></item><item><title>Wigner and Particles</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/003_wigner/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/003_wigner/</guid><description>The Traditional Approach This chapter is to comfort the older physicist who was probably trained on the traditional particles physics approach. In that approach one takes as a catechism the dogma:
The elementary particles are irreducible representations of the fundamental symmetries.
Weinberg&amp;rsquo;s text QFT, Vol.1, Ch.4 goes over Wigner&amp;rsquo;s classification.
The Spacetime Algebra (STA) Approach The Good News: we are not doing anything different in the STA approach to quantum mechanics (QM).</description></item><item><title>T4G Prelims</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/002_preliminaries/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/002_preliminaries/</guid><description>T4G is a research program with no end goal in mind. However, there are some guiding principles and constraints that define the program.
Strictly particles, no fields except one $\Rightarrow$ the field of spacetime, the matter fields are all auxiliary (auxiliary, meaning: needed to account for advanced causation &amp;mdash; or equivalently, non-local correlators &amp;mdash; when adopting a Hamiltonian time evolution). This is a postulate or axiom for the T4G game.</description></item><item><title>T4G Projects</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/001_t4g_projects/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/theory/001_t4g_projects/</guid><description>The philosophy section of this website goes through in a breezy way some of the concepts and possible avenues of research for T4G theory &amp;mdash; all assuming no one has thoroughly debunked all chances of some kind of T4G theory basis for quantum mechanics.
This section of articles gives you just a little taste of some projects I might be working on, time and willing collaborators permitting. Some of these theory chapters are going to be quite long, and the insightful content per paragraph low compared to the Philosophy pages, just because we are now including some mathematical developments.</description></item></channel></rss>