<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Topological 4-Geon Theory Unchained</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/</link><description>Geon Theory Development</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright © 2022, Bijou Murray Smith; All rights reserved.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Schwarz Paws</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/64_schwarzpaws/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/64_schwarzpaws/</guid><description>I was listening to a talk by John Schwarz where he reviewed early String Theory, by &amp;ldquo;early&amp;rdquo; we mean pre-1985. I love this history of recent physics stuff.
These days I do not critique String/M-theory. I think it&amp;rsquo;s a great flavour of theory that describes an alternate reality, but there has got to be a little overlap with our universe, I imagine. As for T4G theory, I can also fancifully imagine T4G wormhole structure is a lot like stringy structure, but of course more constrained.</description></item><item><title>The Hestenes Pill</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/63_hestenespill/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/63_hestenespill/</guid><description>It&amp;rsquo;s not cool to debunk your heroes. I&amp;rsquo;ll try not to. But I recently dug up a David Hestenes talk at the ICACA 2022 Conference .
I could not really follow all of it, but it&amp;rsquo;s worth a comment or two, if for no other reason that to display my ignorance so that people cursorily reading T4GU do not get the false impression I am some genius.
While I&amp;rsquo;m at it, I also browsed a 1993 paper from Hestenes on the “The kinematic origin of complex wavefunctions” which has a bit of a seminal flavour to it, despite being totally ignored by mainstream physicists.</description></item><item><title>Determined Palmer</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/62_determined_palmer/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/62_determined_palmer/</guid><description>Tim Palmer is a smart dude, versed in general relativity, quantum mechanics, fluid dynamics, chaos theory. Like me he thinks the universe operates deterministically. But he is a materialist, so thinks physics determines the lot. I think not.
Anyway, he gave Robinson Erhardt another interview .
Excellent discussion of weather as distinct to climate, and global boiling probabilities in the episode. I have no comment on those topics for now, I agree with Tim.</description></item><item><title>Mind Bends Time</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/61_mind_bend/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/61_mind_bend/</guid><description>Mind Bend Time. My Bed Time. Bed My Time. Bide My Time. Tide On Time. &amp;hellip; I had a bit of a poem going but got stuck in a time loop.
Maybe instead I need a Penrose addition to Rock, Paper, Scissors, Lizard, Spock. Fair game since Spock is not human. It could be Rock, Paper, Scissors, Lizard, Spock, Penrose, Clock.
Clock ages Penrose. Penrose bends Rock. Spock solves Penrose. Penrose tiles Paper.</description></item><item><title>Causal Salad</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/60_causal_settings/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/60_causal_settings/</guid><description>Robinson Erhardt I am almost more interested in this dude than Fay Dowker. He has this low key video podcast here on youtube, manages to get some big names, and always asks great questions for the layperson or educated non-expert audience. Plus, he has an adorable cat that is obviously very fond of him! Makes me envious in a nice way.
Causal Settings Fay Dowker is a world expert on the (CST) Causal Set approach to quantum gravity, and I would never dare to question her judgment on the merits of that theory.</description></item><item><title>Lie Beauty</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/50_lie_beauty/</link><pubDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/50_lie_beauty/</guid><description>TODO: finish this continued series on Clifford algebra for the Standard Model. Even more need to lead-in to some later technical work todo in the theory pages .
I think if I go further it&amp;rsquo;ll have to be a sequel series, with numbering like &amp;ldquo;Lie Fast &amp;amp; Furious II&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Lie Fury III&amp;rdquo; etc.
Octonion Subalgebra I&amp;rsquo;ve long understood the octonion algebra can be found in the spacetime Clifford algebra.</description></item><item><title>Lie Truth</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/49_lie_truth/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/49_lie_truth/</guid><description>TODO: finish this continued series on Clifford algebra for the Standard Model. Need to lead-in to some technical work that&amp;rsquo;ll go later in the theory pages .
Brief Rotor Recap Big Picture What looks promising is that the entire chiral standard model can be expressed by multivector transformations of STA (spacetime algebra) objects.
Lasenby, 2022 got around to finding the octonions within the STA. (I was just about to do this myself, but would have struggled or failed because I did not have Lasenby&amp;rsquo;s characteristic multivector approach to hand.</description></item><item><title>Lie Fury</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/48_lie_fury/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/48_lie_fury/</guid><description>Continuing last post&amp;rsquo;s research notes.
Interlude I did not want to disturb the flow of the algebra posts, but one little interruption is permitted: I was listening to Robinson Erhardt interview Fay Dowker (Causal Set theorist). I had a few observations, so placed them ahead at, Causal Salad .
Plethora of Clifford Algebra Approaches TODO: Run through a short-list of the more interesting &amp;ldquo;Clifford algebra of the Standard Model&amp;rdquo; theorists.</description></item><item><title>Lie Mania</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/47_lie_mania/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/47_lie_mania/</guid><description>Continuing last post&amp;rsquo;s research notes.
QM is a Measurement Theory (Basically my T4G mantra.)
What does this mean? It means, regardless of what the founders of quantum mechanics thought they were doing, they were constructing a theory of measurement and measurement processes.
This is in the axioms but not often pointed out!
I think it can get obscured in the mathematical treatment, which perhaps suffers from a Bourbaki type influence of &amp;ldquo;it&amp;rsquo;s just formalism, nothing more&amp;rdquo; mentality.</description></item><item><title>Measures and Manifolds</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/46_measures_and_manifolds/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/46_measures_and_manifolds/</guid><description>Just a research note on quantum logic today. Plus some lyrics!
Quantum Logic T4G should be able to derive quantum logic. What is quantum logic?
For my purposes QLogic is the logic of measurement propositions under the Heisenberg constraints imposed by non-commuting observables. Quantum logic is the semi-boolean algebra of measurement propositions. By semi-boolean I mean propositions take values in the set $\{0,1\}$ but the distributive rule can fail under some circumstances due to the Heisenberg Uncertainty relations (non-commuting observables) or due to superpositions.</description></item><item><title>Solvable and Unsolvable</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/45_solvableun/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/45_solvableun/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m echoing J.S. Bell&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Speakable and Unspeakable in QM&amp;rdquo; here. Just a short blog for today.
My T4G Work Philosophy There is philosophy of ideas, then there is philosophy of work, which most people just call &amp;ldquo;coping with life and bosses&amp;rdquo; or if you&amp;rsquo;re a lucky little capitalist I guess it&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;coping with those annoying employees who claim they do all the work sheeesh&amp;rdquo;.
For T4G I am grossly under-skilled in methods like string theory and QFT.</description></item><item><title>Spin Helicity Variables</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/44_spinhelicity/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/44_spinhelicity/</guid><description>Following on from the previous article, I wanted to write down some vague thoughts about the scattering amplitude program, or what we&amp;rsquo;re calling the Positive Geometry of Scattering Amplitudes program, or more grandiosely the positive geometry of the real world.
Why Spin Helicity? For me, personally, the Hamiltonian/Lagrangian formulations of QFT are highly abstract. They assume no closed time-like curves, and so information can be propagated off past Cauchy hypersurfaces, among all sorts of other assumptions.</description></item><item><title>All the Forces</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/43_all_forces/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/43_all_forces/</guid><description>This might be out of pedagogical order, since I&amp;rsquo;m gong backwards today to before the Ampltuhedron ( or Positive Geometry) program, back to fundamentals. That&amp;rsquo;s ok, I&amp;rsquo;m blogging here, and it is in any case just preparatory note taking for the theory pages.
In fact today&amp;rsquo;s blog really is just an outline sketch for a theory lecture, or set of lectures. You won&amp;rsquo;t get any of this in any textbook${}^\ast$ circa 2023, so frickin&amp;rsquo; pay attention homies.</description></item><item><title>Bulk Forms</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/42_bulk_forms/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/42_bulk_forms/</guid><description>The blog posts are informal, but this one is probably going to be even more impressionistic than usual, since I&amp;rsquo;m writing today about some fairly inchoate ideas. Friendly warning.
An Appeal If you are an expert on this topic, and see I&amp;rsquo;ve got something horribly wrong, please let me know.
Arkani-Hamed&amp;rsquo;s Amplituhedrons Longer time readers will know I am a big fan of the Amplituhedron program, which I consider to be the rightful heir of the defunct $S$-Matrix program of the 1960&amp;rsquo;s.</description></item><item><title>Wolfemptopy</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/41_wolfemptopy/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/41_wolfemptopy/</guid><description>Something from Machine Learning Street Talk (MLST) today. Comments on an interview with Stephen Wolfram and his attempts to &amp;ldquo;explain&amp;rdquo; entropy.
Note: maybe I&amp;rsquo;ll only use it once or twice, but I&amp;rsquo;m going to adopt a personal convention of using the word Physik for a framework for thinking about physics. I&amp;rsquo;ll use Physics (capital &amp;ldquo;P&amp;rdquo;) for the actual true physics of our realty (which is probably unknowable).
Science aims to get at Physics, but only ever hits Physik.</description></item><item><title>Quantum of Qualia</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/40_thequantum/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/40_thequantum/</guid><description>This week something I feel spiritually akin to, but also think is pretty dopey and far too &amp;ldquo;new agey&amp;rdquo; for my taste. Federico Faggin (soft &amp;ldquo;g&amp;rdquo;) helped invent the first Intel MOS semiconductor chips, and was one of the first engineers to fabricate a hardware neural net. He had a profound experience mid- life which changed his whole attitude to physics and metaphysics. He became somewhat of an Idealist, like that weirdo Donald Hoffman.</description></item><item><title>Explained What?</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/39_explainedsomething/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/39_explainedsomething/</guid><description>This week something from left libertarian pseudo-science field, from the “DemystifySci Podcast” . A bit of a freak show, but in a good way and fascinating.
BTW: I found DemystifySci a long time ago, but stumbled on it again from a clicking on ecological macroeconomics stuff, where I found the interview with farmer&amp;ndash;biologist Dr. Shane Simonsen , Zero Input Agriculture fame (a total clickbait meme if ever there was one). But Shane is an ok guy.</description></item><item><title>Envariance</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/38_envariance/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/38_envariance/</guid><description>Alt Title: Classical Physics Regained Envariance is Wojciech Zurek&amp;rsquo;s term for &amp;ldquo;entanglement assisted invariance&amp;rdquo;. Zurek uses this notion to derive the Born Rule without appealing to environmental decoherence. (He was an earlier proponent of decoherence theory of classical reality, an approach that makes the wave-function collapse problem go away). The envariance approach is however still a form of decoherence.
Envariance and T4G I tend to only skim Zurek&amp;rsquo;s papers, because they are not terribly useful for T4G theory, but the basic idea here resonates to me.</description></item><item><title>The Other DougBot</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/37_otherdougbot/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/37_otherdougbot/</guid><description>Dammit all! The inevitable happened and one of my favourite writers of all time, Douglas R Hofstadter, did a webinar/interview on the recent Ai advances. Total banana brain stuff. So although I am completely counter-paradigm to mainstream academia here, I have to comment for anyone who cares to read. Can I make my case against Brains being sources of consciousness? No. But you can&amp;rsquo;t make the affirmative case either.
Which means we&amp;rsquo;re arguing metaphysics (if you care to argue against me).</description></item><item><title>Retrocauschmality</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/36_retrocauseschmality/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/36_retrocauseschmality/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve written about retrocausality before, but a recent essay by Huw Price and Ken Wharton in Aeon Magazine gives me some licence to go over it again, with added nuances.
Retrocausality &amp;ldquo;Solves&amp;rdquo; Bell Entanglement Yeah. But it is a non-solution by my book. However, I like Price &amp;amp; Wharton&amp;rsquo;s resolution. It&amp;rsquo;s half-elegant and logically impeccable. It&amp;rsquo;s the half-nonelegance that bugs me.
Before I go through the logic, the big picture overview is that in QM we get irreconcilable paradoxes if we hold on to simply three or four classical physics principles, nay, not even paradoxes, they are just pure logical inconsistencies that can never be resolved.</description></item><item><title>VMs All the Way Down</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/35_vms_allthewaydown/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/35_vms_allthewaydown/</guid><description>Now that some extremes of Ai fear &amp;amp; loathing have calmed down to the relatively mild levels of only existential panic for human beings, not mice, I was happy to get back to some physics and find a Quanta Magazine report on Causal Dynamical Triangulations (CDT) that I thought was worth blogging about. See “The Digital Quest for Quantum Gravity” .
Mann-Gell Steel-manning I don&amp;rsquo;t feel the need to issue a bunch of qualifiers like &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m not an expert on CDT, but&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;.</description></item><item><title>Darwinian Dualism?</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/34_darwin/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/34_darwin/</guid><description>You knew it had to happen, at some point in blogging about science I was going to write about Darwinism. Don&amp;rsquo;t worry, it is good and bad. Something for everyone. I will refer to an interview with Denis Noble here at IAI as a launching pad.
Teasers I&amp;rsquo;ll start with my hot takes on the interview with Denis Noble. I&amp;rsquo;d describe him as a science nerd who understands little about metaphysics, but a lot about his narrow speciality field of research.</description></item><item><title>Double Time</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/33_doubleslit_time/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/33_doubleslit_time/</guid><description>Nice to have a break from AI today. Ben Miles (here) had me alerted to the temporal double slit experiments. I had heard of these before, but it is great that optics labs are now able to perform the experiments cleanly. You can read one paper on it here , and another one here unfortunately behind the Nature paywall. Whatever happened to public funded science being publicly accessible? The latter team are at Kings College London, not IBM.</description></item><item><title>Making Misteaks</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/32_mistakes/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/32_mistakes/</guid><description>Yes, yes, I know, &amp;ldquo;Not another AI post!&amp;rdquo; It&amp;rsquo;s the zeitgeist making me do it yo'.
Seriously though, it is nice and chill to listen to Radiohead and write these articles no one is reading on the current AI flurry of generative tools and fear &amp;amp; panic. I do not write as a contrarian for the sake of it, I have a clear moral purpose in philosophising against the grain of almost all of AI academia and tech-utopia activism.</description></item><item><title>Anti-Turing tests</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/31_antituring/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/31_antituring/</guid><description>Following on the series of AI topics, over at Ōhanga Pai I had promised a mini-series on what we can expect advanced AI to accomplish. Today I want to take a step back from the macroeconomics and do another philosophy post, but related. I want to lay out my positions on whether it is even sensible to try to define &amp;ldquo;consciousness&amp;rdquo; and if so, even if only partially, how you might &amp;ldquo;test&amp;rdquo; for consciousness.</description></item><item><title>Singular Limits</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/30_singular_limits/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/30_singular_limits/</guid><description>Came across a couple of good Machine Language Street Talk episodes that had me thinking about limits of computer generated &amp;ldquo;intelligence&amp;rdquo;. One was a short talk with Prof. Walid Saba that touched on issues of the infinite and the stark difference between recursion and recurrence, “Can ChatGPT Handle Infinite Possibilities?” . The other was an interview with author David Foster on his expansive knowledge of ML and “Future of Generative AI” .</description></item><item><title>Retrocausality-schmality</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/29_retrocausalityschmality/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/29_retrocausalityschmality/</guid><description>Online doktor of physics and phys-ed, Dr Ben Miles, put up this useful video essay recently: “Why Physicists Think The Future Changes the Past - Retrocausality Explained” .
Spoilers:
He does not explain retrocausality.
He mentions only that retrocausality could allow for retaining both locality and realism in quantum mechanics theory. He does not say how retrocausality is achieved, or whether it is a thing. I&amp;rsquo;m here to show you we do not even need it.</description></item><item><title>Susy C</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/28_susy/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/28_susy/</guid><description>One of the joys of writing theoretical physics blogs from outside academia is I can more fluidly change my mind without embarrassment or long-winded papers explaining why. Heck, most physics academic publishing is not supposed to be about opinions and sci-gossip at all (the kind of gossip I like: gossip about ideas, not about people). But on the arXiv especially, these days, we do find an awful lot of speculation and fantasy, which is something like 50% opinion, dressed up as research output.</description></item><item><title>The Aharonov–Susskind Hand Wave</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/27_aharonov_susskind/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/27_aharonov_susskind/</guid><description>This week I get to comment on my almost all-time favourite physicist, Lenny Susskind. And no need to think me weird for watching Susskind lectures as my dominant form of entertainment &amp;mdash; the rest of you are watching HBO, Disney and Netflix saccharin, so how is that less weird?
The excerpt is from TTM Lecture-2 of the course “Particle Physics 3: Supersymmetry and Grand Unification” .
This post is also a bleeding of my theory pages into the blog.</description></item><item><title>Non-Kolmogorov and Planck Microscopes</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/26_nonkolmogorov/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/26_nonkolmogorov/</guid><description>Comments on an interview with the weird-platonist Wolfgang Smith . (Not my cup of tea platonist.)
So I dropped a comment on that interview.
Why I Think There is No &amp;ldquo;Measurement Problem&amp;rdquo; There is no &amp;ldquo;measurement problem&amp;rdquo; to solve really. The wave function is a fiction, an accounting device. A cobordism between two Cauchy hypersurfaces is not determined by the past surface data thanks to off-shell processes. So there is only ever a statistical description${}^\dagger$.</description></item><item><title>Formal Models</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/25_formal_models/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/25_formal_models/</guid><description>Comments on an interview with Edward Frenkel here .
Is Reality a Paradox? No. Not unless what you think of as &amp;ldquo;reality&amp;rdquo; is what you think reality is. In which case you&amp;rsquo;re nuts. Like Nietzsche${}^\dagger$.
Frenkel says (in fewer words) mathematical theories are pretty fixed in immutable divine marble and granite, they&amp;rsquo;re independent of physical reality. And I would agree. Although I might add, we depend upon physical forms for our current existence and hence our current fallible not-fixed-in-granite mental grasp on mathematics.</description></item><item><title>Free Botherations</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/24_freebotherations/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/24_freebotherations/</guid><description>All this distraction writing about AI and platonism is sucking my time away from macroeconomics and T4G, but I hope for posterity all these musing are useful to some kids who might get some inspiration. Today The Algorithm took me to Machine Learning Street Talk and an interesting interview with Karl Friston , an eminent neuroscientist who has some wacky ideas about cognition, relevant to AI and to the anti-platonistic schools of thought.</description></item><item><title>Computational Geons</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/23_pygeons/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/23_pygeons/</guid><description>No, this is not a post about how the structure of physical reality lives in a computer. It is a lot more mundane.
Do Not Force Your Model It&amp;rsquo;s always a delight to learn mathematics tricks. Paul Cohen&amp;rsquo;s Forcing methods for example. One form of which is: given a model $M$ for set theory (ZFC) there is a larger structure $N \supseteq M$ which can form a model of (ZFC + $\neg B$) where $\neg B$ is the negation of some desired theorem.</description></item><item><title>Sabina Caveina</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/22_sabinafail/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/22_sabinafail/</guid><description>&amp;ldquo;Sometimes the only scientific answer we can give is ‘We don&amp;rsquo;t know’.&amp;rdquo;
&amp;mdash; Sabine Hossenfelder, from Existential Physics: A Scientist&amp;#39;s Guide to Life&amp;#39;s Biggest Questions. I love Sabina Hossenfelder, she&amp;rsquo;s one of the emerging great science communicators and popularizers of our generation (go Gen-X, we&amp;rsquo;re not done with extinguishing our neoliberal heritage just yet).
However, this week she had a major fail. Fortunately it is in philosophy and ethics, so not a big deal.</description></item><item><title>Susskinistas</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/21_susskinistas/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/21_susskinistas/</guid><description>&amp;ldquo;Gravity does not seem to be a thing that you quantize.&amp;rdquo;
&amp;mdash; Lenny Susskind , 2019. There&amp;rsquo;s a helpful little youtube channel posting physics stuff here: Emergence . Looks like they&amp;rsquo;re like me, Susskinistas. So thought it time to write more about Susskind. His ideas, not the man himself.
Over lunchtimes I was enjoying re-watching a couple, one on “Leonard Susskind astonishing lecture on debunking quantum gravity” and another just a conversation “Leonard Susskind astonishing podcast on String Theory, ADS/CFT, Gravity, Holography and more” (sounds like that one was clipped from a Sean Carroll podcast episode) and as I posted there, I love the clickbait titles when they&amp;rsquo;re kinda&amp;rsquo; accurate!</description></item><item><title>True Platonics</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/20_platonics/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/20_platonics/</guid><description>Last post I wrote about the hazards of platonification (falsely using platonic ideals when they are not applicable) also known as essentialism (of a bad variety), namely when there is no essence). This week I write an apologia.
How Platonism is True When there are essences, platonistic thinking is good. Even true.
When Are There Essences? First, what the heck is &amp;ldquo;an essence&amp;rdquo;? That&amp;rsquo;s a whole thesis, and kind of pointless.</description></item><item><title>Plates and Socks</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/19_plates_and_socks/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/19_plates_and_socks/</guid><description>After the vigorous review of Carlo Rovelli&amp;rsquo;s book, plus a lot of previous writings, I feel inclined to explain my apparent sympathy with platonism. Most platonists will not need to bother reading this one, but those who believe platonism is an evil might be advised to hear me out.
This will be a little polemic, deliberately, in order to afford myself brevity. I&amp;rsquo;m sure sympathetic readers can fill in the nuances for themselves.</description></item><item><title>Canned Cannelloni</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/18_canned_cannelloni/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/18_canned_cannelloni/</guid><description>Finishing the occasional blog series on Carlo Rovelli&amp;rsquo;s little book Helgoland . The final product of our quantum cookery has to be horrifically canned because we do not have infinite free time to keep rolling out the cannelloni.
Deep Relationalism Last post I mentioned how ultimately a relational view in metaphysics is probably always possible, but if you are like me this is still contingent upon One Absolute (Cantors&amp;rsquo; Absolute Infinite or the Divine Creator in religious parlance, or Spinoza&amp;rsquo;s Universe).</description></item><item><title>Lenin's Lasagna</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/17_lenins_lasagna/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/17_lenins_lasagna/</guid><description>Continuing the occasional blog series on Carlo Rovelli&amp;rsquo;s little book Helgoland . The story takes a little twist today into political philosophy, although only metaphors for the quantum world, it&amp;rsquo;s perhaps a useful diversion.
Can Idealism Exist Alongside Materialism? In Part-V Rovelli starts talking about some Bolshevik history, and uses the protagonists Aleksandr Bogdanov (Aleksandr Malinovskij) and Vladimir Lenin as a bit of an allegory for getting across to his readers the subtle and sometimes fluid discrimination between materialism and idealism.</description></item><item><title>The Pattern in the Penne</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/16_pattern_in_penne/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/16_pattern_in_penne/</guid><description>Continuing the occasional blog series on Carlo Rovelli&amp;rsquo;s little book Helgoland , wherein we look for where the ripples (information) get written into the rigatoni.
Substrates Matter We have to build our rigatoni from something, otherwise our lovers starve.
On pages 90&amp;ndash;94 Rovelli introduces the reader to the physics or computer science definition of information. He then claims it&amp;rsquo;s different in classical mechanics compared to quantum mechanics. The basic idea is the same, since Rovelli admits information is relative in classical mechanics already (no quibble with that).</description></item><item><title>EPR Macaroni</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/15_epr_macaroni/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/15_epr_macaroni/</guid><description>Continuing the occasional blog series on Carlo Rovelli&amp;rsquo;s little book Helgoland . On the same bat-channel today, Rovelli fails to cook the macaroni wormholes.
Rovelli&amp;rsquo;s Lovers Starve Themselves Pages 81-89 or Part-IV is where Rovelli gives me a little bit to chew on. I was waiting for this, because my suspicion all along has been that Carlo does not understand the output from AdS/CFT gauge-gravity duality and ER=EPR conjectures. These are still conjectures mind you, but Loop Quantum Gravity is a whole lot more conjectural, so I&amp;rsquo;m not quite sure why Rovelli seems to not comprehend Susskind&amp;rsquo;s work.</description></item><item><title>Sauce Me</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/14_sauceme/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/14_sauceme/</guid><description>Continuing the occasional blog series on Carlo Rovelli&amp;rsquo;s little book Helgoland . Today, the full dish of pasta on RIQM, in which we find some bovine proteins masquerading as seafood.
Rovelli&amp;rsquo;s Limb Page 73&amp;ndash;74 is where Carlo dishes out the full meal. He combines the interactionism (nothing has properties until it interacts) and relationism (no objective states exist) in a fell swoop of philosophy, figuratively decapitating the hapless weakling chickens of Coping-hagen for his pasta stew.</description></item><item><title>I'd Like to Buy Some Cheese</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/13_idliketobuysomecheese/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/13_idliketobuysomecheese/</guid><description>Continuing the occasional blog series on Carlo Rovelli&amp;rsquo;s little book Helgoland . Today, searching for a tasty bit of cheddar, or any damn cheese to grate on our pasta.
How is Relationalism &amp;ldquo;Quantum&amp;rdquo;? By page 69 we have still not got any better explanation for why relational physics is inherently quantum mechanical or in any way explains appearances. Carlo&amp;rsquo;s next effort is,
&amp;ldquo;The discovery of quantum theory, I believe, is the discovery that the properties of any entity are nothing other than the way in which that entity influences others.</description></item><item><title>The Sauce-Pasta-Gourmet Relations</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/12_saucepastegourmet/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/12_saucepastegourmet/</guid><description>Continuing the occasional blog series on Carlo Rovelli&amp;rsquo;s little book Helgoland . Today we begin on Rovelli&amp;rsquo;s Relational Interpretation (RI, or RIQM) of quantum mechanics.
Sour Sauce Basis The tomatoes Carlo is using for his sauce start off a bit suspect, because his italicized defining concept for Relationalism is,
&amp;ldquo;What quantum theory describes&amp;hellip; is the way in which one part of nature manifests itself to any other single part of nature.</description></item><item><title>Spaghetti Qwesterns</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/11_spaghetti_worlds/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/11_spaghetti_worlds/</guid><description>Continuing the occasional blog series on Carlo Rovelli&amp;rsquo;s little book Helgoland . Today some remarks on Carlo&amp;rsquo;s takes on the standard competing interpretations of quantum mechanics.
First up, my admitted bias is to treat the wave function (and the fields in QFT) as epistemical, not ontological, and I think this aligns with Carlo. But it&amp;rsquo;s not that we&amp;rsquo;re rejecting Many Worlds (treats the wave function as reality) or the Bohm Pilot Wave (treats the wave function as hidden, but causal).</description></item><item><title>Rovelli Ravioli</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/10_rovelli_ravioli/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/10_rovelli_ravioli/</guid><description>This will begin a new occasional blog series on Carlo Rovelli&amp;rsquo;s little book Helgoland which is a materialistic although poetic journey through the history of quantum mechanics. It has nothing on Feynman&amp;rsquo;s classic QED: The Strange Theory of Light and Matter but I can&amp;rsquo;t hold that against Carlo.
Like a great chef, Carlo serves up tasty treats, but if you are a vegan purist for spacetime physics like T4GU aficionados then some of Rovelli&amp;rsquo;s ravioli are going to be a bit smelly, beefy and too cheesy.</description></item><item><title>No Look Measurements</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/09_no_look_measurements/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/09_no_look_measurements/</guid><description>I encourage you to subscribe to Sabine Hossenfelder&amp;#39;s newsletter here , you can also see her do the science news on youtube. It is pretty good.
On the 13 January Edition she talks about so- called &amp;ldquo;interaction free measurements&amp;rdquo;. Which is typical hyped jargon from the capitalist profit-driven or grant-funding gladiatorial arena of academia. But I&amp;rsquo;m not one to begrudge Wheelerisms and quark-colour and whatnot, it&amp;rsquo;s harmless fun to hype. The original concepts permitted by QM were called &amp;ldquo;non-destructive bomb tests&amp;rdquo; (Elitzur-Vaidman ) so maybe we&amp;rsquo;ve dialed down the hype a bit since then.</description></item><item><title>Minds and Brains - 2</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/08_minds_brains_2/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/08_minds_brains_2/</guid><description>This is just an article stub for now. Continuing some themes from Minds and Brains - 1 .
Semantics is not Semantics Everyone sane believes syntax cannot generate semantics. In the world of machine behaviorism this is the idea that only encoding rules for syntactical correctness does not give a programmed system &amp;mdash; even one equipped with a RNG &amp;mdash; access to semantic comprehension. That is an engineer&amp;rsquo;s understanding. Mark Bishop is an archetype here.</description></item><item><title>Spin Gauge Theories and GA</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/07_spin_gauge_ga/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/07_spin_gauge_ga/</guid><description>This post is more a personal note for my own reference. I should write a Philosophy page on this. I am procrastinating here, because I am supposed to be writing the Theory chapter on the Hestenes spinors, but now I want to call them Pezzaglia-Lounesto spinors, but that might upset the GA community apple cart? They are the same things, in mathematical physics, but make a bit of a difference in quantum mechanics.</description></item><item><title>Minds and Brains - 1</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/06_minds_brains/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/06_minds_brains/</guid><description>I had to get some thoughts down on some follow-ups to the previous post, so here we are, into questions about consciousness. A very dicey topic and not really appropriate for T4GU, but I have not got a Philosophy of Mind github yet, because I do not plan on any such software (what would that even be? Yet another chatbot? Not interested my dudes. Needless duplication of effort for paychecks.)</description></item><item><title>Thoughts on chatGPT and Related</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/05_chatgpt/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/05_chatgpt/</guid><description>I do not want to write about metaphysics too much for T4GU, that&amp;rsquo;s a retirement proper project (when I am properly retired and need no new income). However, Internet friend Curt Jaimungal from the Theories of Everything channel gave me advanced notice he was going to interview the &amp;ldquo;chatGPT guy&amp;rdquo; and asked if I&amp;rsquo;d have any questions for this dude. So this is a fair enough excuse to expound upon a bit of philosophy that is only very loosely related to T4GU (at least insofar as any theory of fundamental physics ontology has something to say about metaphysics, or just the possibility of metaphysics &amp;mdash; which should not be too much if we are being dutifully humble and honest).</description></item><item><title>Sidney Coleman and John von Neumann</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/04_coleman_vonneumann/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/04_coleman_vonneumann/</guid><description>Any of you like to watch physics youtubes for lunch?
Here is a nice legacy one, complete with 1990&amp;rsquo;s blurry slides by Sidney Coleman (a renowned pretty good teacher). Coupl&amp;rsquo;a things:
About 18 min in Coleman relates how John von Neumann dismissed the idea QM was distinct to CM by virtue of being &amp;ldquo;probabilistic&amp;rdquo; and instead suggested the key distinction is that QM has &amp;ldquo;non-commuting observables&amp;rdquo;. Was von Neumann correct?</description></item><item><title>Nuances in writing about T4GU</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/03_nuances_tg4_writing/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/03_nuances_tg4_writing/</guid><description>The previous post was hopefully not reading like a rant against QFT. I took care to note that QFT could be fundamental but also tried to make the case that QFT is basically a statistical correlation function theory, which can only be regarded as base ontology if &amp;ldquo;God Plays Dice.&amp;rdquo;
It is a moral (an &amp;ldquo;ought to be&amp;rdquo;) stance that I take on such matters, where I side with John Bell and Einstein, and favour a realist ontology that is only statistical because we cannot know the exact causal inputs.</description></item><item><title>Why QFT is not fundamental</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/02_why_fields/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/02_why_fields/</guid><description>&amp;hellip; and how QFT could have been fundamental Internet friend Curt Jaimungal of the Theories of Everything channel asked for my opinion on why I think fields are fictional. So here is an essay format reply.
Why Fields? I think fields are necessary for computing anything remotely useful from &amp;ldquo;near-to fundamental&amp;rdquo; physics. This includes quantities like the electron magnetic moment and fundamental masses, and basic elementary scattering amplitudes, and whatnot.</description></item><item><title>Scattered Thoughts</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/01_scattered_thoughts/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/01_scattered_thoughts/</guid><description>Thought I&amp;rsquo;d start the blog with a bit of a journal. A lot of the latter stuff in this file might be fairly recent thought, so not exactly in chronological order with the rest of this blog.
Multivector Fields In quantum theory we introduce fields as fictional accounting tools. Why? Maybe they are real?
Yeah, ok, see the next blog article , perhaps they&amp;rsquo;re real. But I have no truck with that, it seems too weird.</description></item><item><title>Introduction to Geon Theory</title><link>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/00_intro_to_t4gu/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://4geons.github.io/t4gu/blog/00_intro_to_t4gu/</guid><description>Geon Theory is a pretty minimal extension of general relativity that purports to derive most of the basic phenomenology of quantum mechanics. Rather than &amp;ldquo;general relativity from quantum mechanics&amp;rdquo; we are attempting &amp;ldquo;QM from GR&amp;rdquo;. The foundations for this work come from Mark Hadley&amp;rsquo;s thesis, Quantum Mechanics from General Relativity and the recent research on AdS/CFT and gauge&amp;ndash;gravity duality, which Leonard Susskind has characterized by ER=EPR and GR=QM .</description></item></channel></rss>