<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Topological 4-Geon Theory Unchained</title><link>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/</link><description>Geon Theory Development</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright © 2022, Bijou Murray Smith; All rights reserved.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Gravitons II</title><link>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/016_gravitons_ii/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/016_gravitons_ii/</guid><description>Had a few vague thoughts, this is just a rough note on them.
Spacetime algebra and Positive Geometry I was thinking about geometric algebra, how I think of the spinors as not &amp;ldquo;the fermions&amp;rdquo; but rather as instructions for transforming laboratory coordinates to particle frames, in such a way so that the usual operators for observables work in the formalism to mathematically &amp;ldquo;record&amp;rdquo; the associated observable.
Then I was wondering about the program formerly known as Amplituhedrons, now known as the Positive Geometry of the Real World (PGRW) program.</description></item><item><title>Can Free Will Be a Thing?</title><link>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/100_free_will/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/100_free_will/</guid><description>Disclaimer: I wrote a lot of this philosophy in the 1990&amp;rsquo;s before hugo was around, and this particular post in 2021. But I&amp;rsquo;ll be using the datetime to order them in hugo . So don&amp;rsquo;t take the dates too literally, they&amp;rsquo;re just for time-ordering, until I figure a different hugo rendering for chapter ordering.
Does T4G Theory Permit &amp;ldquo;Free Will&amp;rdquo;? Short answer is a qualified, &amp;ldquo;Yes it does.&amp;rdquo;
Long answer is that it depends on what you mean by &amp;ldquo;free will.</description></item><item><title>What's the Devil Again?</title><link>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/015_whatsmassagain/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/015_whatsmassagain/</guid><description>Last two chapters I&amp;rsquo;ve been ruminating over mass, or more generally charge. I rewatched some old Susskind and had a much clearer mental picture, and will try to again relate it to T4G theory. Susskind of course provides a field theory picture, which has to at least be consistent with T4G in some sort of mapping from 4-geons (topology view) to their statistics (field theory view).
Usual Caveats Reading level: undergrad or advanced high school.</description></item><item><title>Is T4G a Bootstrap?</title><link>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/099_is_tg4_a_bootstrap/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/099_is_tg4_a_bootstrap/</guid><description>How T4G Could be a Bootstrap First, no. No, I do not think T4G bootstraps.
But it could be thought of as a bootstrapping idea. How?
It is because how would one motivate non-trivial spacetime topology in the first place?
One answer is to apply Wheeler&amp;rsquo;s spacetime foam idea to Einstein gravity. But that&amp;rsquo;s cheating. That&amp;rsquo;s using quantum mechanics to say 4-geon theory is the right idea.
The way I take this is as a consistency argument, not a justification.</description></item><item><title>Charge without Field</title><link>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/014_chargenocharge/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/014_chargenocharge/</guid><description>Following on from the previous loosey-goosey chapter on mass and length relations, I want to continue with the theme in the spirit of John Archilbald Wheeler, which is to now consider how charge without charge can be motivated. Or specifically how can we get charge from topology?
To do this I want to reboot Wheeler.
Caveats Reading level: undergrad or advanced high school. Professionals should go elsewhere.
All of this is preliminary to the T4GU theory pages, which I have not yet fleshed out.</description></item><item><title>Smarticles</title><link>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/013_smarticles/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/013_smarticles/</guid><description>This is a series of short notes, had to jot them down for the record. Turned into a long one.
T4G theory postulates that the elementary particles are topologically non- trivial regions of spacetime. If they contain internal ER bridges (wormhole substructure) then they are &amp;ldquo;stringy&amp;rdquo;. If they contain internal ER structure that can be self-entangled across large space and possibly time intervals, then there is (probably) no need to have an emergent spacetime theory.</description></item><item><title>Emergent spacetime</title><link>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/012_emergent_spacetime/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/012_emergent_spacetime/</guid><description>What Emerges? It is very trendy these days to adopt the holographic conception of physics and claim that the fundamental reality is a field theory on the boundary, and that spacetime in the bulk is &amp;ldquo;emergent&amp;rdquo;. But what does this mean?
Given the dual descriptions are equivalences, it means nothing truly &amp;ldquo;emerges.&amp;rdquo;
However, physicists have a hard time thinking about how quantum mechanics can have anything to do with spacetime as described in general relativity, so they tend to want to regard entanglement and other &amp;ldquo;quantum&amp;rdquo; phenomena as more fundamental than the spacetime.</description></item><item><title>Gravitons</title><link>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/011_gravitons/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/011_gravitons/</guid><description>Gravitons &amp;mdash; are they not &amp;ldquo;thoroughly quantum&amp;rdquo;? The most convincing argument that gravitons (spin-2 bosons) are &amp;ldquo;more fundamental&amp;rdquo; than spacetime (than GR) was in an article which I cannot retrieve or recall the title of, but below I&amp;rsquo;ve linked to an alternative.
This is a little bit different, and more serious an objection, to Weinberg&amp;#39;s seminal articles (and here ) on photons and gravitons in $S$-matrix theory. In Weinberg&amp;rsquo;s papers he shows how spin-1 and spin-2 bosons are the only force- carrying (universal coupling) particle fields consistent with quantum mechanics in 4D spacetime (&amp;quot;&amp;hellip; there are no macroscopic fields corresponding to particles of spin 3 or higher.</description></item><item><title>Pauli Exclusion and T4G</title><link>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/010_pauli_exclusion/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/010_pauli_exclusion/</guid><description>Pauli Exclusion &amp;mdash; is it not &amp;ldquo;thoroughly quantum&amp;rdquo;? One noobie objection to T4G is that fermions do not exist in GR, and so also the Pauli Exclusion Principle cannot be derived from GR. The first assertion is false, as we&amp;rsquo;ve already shown: in the geometric spacetime algebra (STA) fermions occur naturally as the generators of rotations and Lorentz boosts.
The concept of &amp;ldquo;a fermion&amp;rdquo; is just a unit of matter which has the same symmetries as the rotation generators.</description></item><item><title>Wormholes and T4G</title><link>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/009_wormholes/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/009_wormholes/</guid><description>Wormholes and T4G T4G postulates that elementary particles are regions of non-trivial spacetime topology. In the generic case this implies a wormhole topology, at least at about the Planck scale.
But classical GR forbids wormholes by the energy condition on matter. The most relaxed constraint possible seems to be the average null energy condition, $$ \int_{-\infty}^{\infty} dx^+\, T_{++} \ge 0$$ which says the integral of $T_{++}$ has to be positive, or equivalently, that there is no faster path between any two points in spacetime than a fastest light ray path.</description></item><item><title>Black Holes and T4G</title><link>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/008_black_holes_and_t4g/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/008_black_holes_and_t4g/</guid><description>Aren&amp;rsquo;t Black Holes Nowadays &amp;ldquo;Totally Quantum&amp;rdquo;? Yes, black holes are deeply quantum mechanical objects. But T4G is already a quantum theory and so most of the holography results will go through unchanged from the various semi-classical field approximations in QFT and AdS/CFT over to T4G theory.
In the previous chapter I mentioned there&amp;rsquo;d be a twist in the Classical Mechanics from Quantum Mechanics story. The twist is that black holes occur in both QM and CM, and so the &amp;ldquo;measurement problem&amp;rdquo; actually does not entirely &amp;ldquo;go away&amp;rdquo; in CM just because $\hbar\rightarrow 0$.</description></item><item><title>The amplitudes had to be complex</title><link>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/007_amplitudes_hadtobe_complex/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/007_amplitudes_hadtobe_complex/</guid><description>The easy way This is a short post on &amp;ldquo;why complex amplitudes?&amp;rdquo;
I&amp;rsquo;ll refer you to Scott Aaronson&amp;rsquo;s blog, Shetl Optimized. The idea here is that we have little option but to employ complex numbers for the QM amplitudes. No other algebraic field works.
In other words, the &amp;ldquo;proof&amp;rdquo; that T4G theory implies geometric amplitudes could be as simple as verifying the logic is the same as quantum logic, so no nasty dynamical theory proof or derivation may be needed (although it&amp;rsquo;d also be desirable at some point).</description></item><item><title>Geometric Amplitudes</title><link>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/006_geometric_amplitudes/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/006_geometric_amplitudes/</guid><description>Going to be a but &amp;ldquo;dumb&amp;rdquo; or deliberately naïve here for pedagogical purposes. I want readers to figure things out for themselves. I&amp;rsquo;m just giving some prompts, and I am sure some of them will be unwittingly misleading. But whacannido?
Complex or Geometic Amplitudes? In a Hilbert (vector) space formulation of a Measurement Theory the probability amplitudes have to be complex-valued, because there is no other option.
Scott Aaronsen, among others, teaches that if the algebra is extended over quaternions or any higher algebra, then faster-than-light signalling is possible.</description></item><item><title>A T4G Account of Superposition</title><link>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/005_t4g_account_of_superposition/</link><pubDate>Mon, 26 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/005_t4g_account_of_superposition/</guid><description>The Basic Problem Reviewed Recall the story so far: we can account for superpositions in T4G theory with wormhole gas (WHG) dynamics. But it is harder to see how wave equations are effective solutions, because having superposed alternatives in a sum-over-histories (SOH) is not a trivial thing to compute or derive in T4G, since it &amp;ldquo;has&amp;rdquo; to be derived from spacetime topology fine structure. Although when I write &amp;ldquo;has to be&amp;rdquo; that only means what we&amp;rsquo;d ideally like, not what is possible.</description></item><item><title>Sums Over Histories</title><link>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/004_sum_over_histories/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/004_sum_over_histories/</guid><description>T4G and Feynman Path Integrals In the last chapter, Problem of Interference, we considered how superposition could be derived from the wormhole gas hypothesis (WHG) in T4G theory, or from self-entanglement. One possibility floated was that a Lorentzian wormhole gas topology allows 4-geons to &amp;ldquo;time travel&amp;rdquo; in effect, although in a highly constrained way &amp;mdash; basically consistent with &amp;ldquo;no-signalling&amp;rdquo;.
No-signalling is a lynchpin of quantum mechanics. It holds in T4G theory because the wormhole bridges are minimal, so one cannot use a T4G wormhole to send useful information faster than light.</description></item><item><title>The Problem of Interference</title><link>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/003_problem_of_interference/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/003_problem_of_interference/</guid><description>Entanglement and Superposition In orthodox QM it is often thought the really weird thing is entanglement. In T4G theory entanglement is simple, it&amp;rsquo;s described by ER=EPR, that is to say, spacetime topology can account for entanglement.
Most physicists would suspect entanglement is closely related to superposition, but no one ever says how, exactly. This is also a bit of a problem for Geon Theory. It is not immediately clear how entanglement can account for superpositions.</description></item><item><title>Basic T4G Theory</title><link>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/001_basic_t4g/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://t4gu.gitlab.io/t4gu/philosophy/001_basic_t4g/</guid><description>Disclaimer: I wrote a lot of this philosophy in the 1990&amp;rsquo;s before Hugo was around, and this particular post in 2021. But I&amp;rsquo;ll be using the datetime to order them in Hugo . So don&amp;rsquo;t take the dates too literally, they&amp;rsquo;re just for time-ordering, until I figure a different hugo rendering for chapter ordering.
All my writing is a story, so I do encourage newcomers to read from top to bottom of the TOCs.</description></item></channel></rss>